<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The slaughter-house, or, A brief description of the Spanish Inquisition, in a method never before used in which is laid open the tyranny, insolence, perfidiousness, and barbarous cruelty of that tribunal, detected by several examples and observations / gathered together by the pains and study of James Salgado, a converted Spanish priest ...</title>
            <author>Salgado, James, fl. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S381A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12490685</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12490685</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62369</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62369)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 290:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The slaughter-house, or, A brief description of the Spanish Inquisition, in a method never before used in which is laid open the tyranny, insolence, perfidiousness, and barbarous cruelty of that tribunal, detected by several examples and observations / gathered together by the pains and study of James Salgado, a converted Spanish priest ...</title>
                  <author>Salgado, James, fl. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inquisition --  Spain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62369:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62369:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Slaughter-houſe,</hi> Or a Brief DESCRIPTION OF THE Spaniſh Inquiſition, IN A Method never before uſed; In which is laid open The Tyranny, Inſolence, Perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Barbarous Cruelty of that TRIBUNAL; Detected by ſeveral Examples and Obſervations.</p>
            <p>Gathered together by the Pains and Study of <hi>JAMES SALGADO</hi> a Converted Spaniſh Prieſt; who beareth in his Body the Prints of their Inhuman rigors.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 11.33.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Obturaverunt Or a Leonum.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>T.B.</hi> for the Author</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62369:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62369:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Serene and Mighty CHARLES the II. By the Grace of God of <hi>Great Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your moſt Excellent Majeſty.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Should condemn my ſelf as an Offender, if I carried this ſhort Deſcription of the moſt Unjuſt Court, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition</hi> to any other Sanctuary than your Sacred Feet. What I have here drawn, is the Portraict of thoſe Inquiſitors who denied me, and others, the Liberty of our Conſcience, and choice of our Religion, and threatned my
<pb facs="tcp:62369:3"/>Life for being true to my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, my Conſcience, and the hopes of Heaven: To you, Great Sir, I dedicate them, who are the Defender of my Life, and of the Liberty of my undiſſembled Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. I have found, what Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes have heard, the Royal Clemency and Favour you bear towards afflicted <hi>Proteſtants; France</hi> and other Nations are your Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; and I a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> reſcued firſt from the Errours of Popery, next from the Cruelties of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, and flying to your Royal Clemency as to the Tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Diſtreſſed Converts and Proteſtants, implore your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this Piece, a Witneſs of
<pb facs="tcp:62369:3"/>that Divine Zeal which you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways expreſs towards True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Profeſſors of it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom God hath merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made me one, and your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty hath preſerved me under your Government and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; for which, and for the many Royal Favours done to Proteſtants, continual Prayers are and will be made for your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Long Life, Proſperous Reign, and Eternal Happineſs, by all the Churches of God; and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, as by duty more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thereunto bound, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted Suppliant, <hi>James Salgado.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62369:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kind Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Judge it not very needful to ſtop thee with a long Preface, which is but the firſt part of it's following Dſicourſe; what I have written here, I have written with an upright heart, I neither deſign an injury to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,</hi> nor a praiſe to my ſeuf: Thou mayst peruſe and imploy it to thine own profit, and in thy Chriſtian Candour think favourably towards</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine,<hi>James Salgado.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62369:4"/>
            <head>THE Slaughter-houſe.</head>
            <p>LEST any one ſhould ſurmiſe I am writing this ſhort Story out of any private reſpects, I do in the entrance thereof ſolemnly proteſt before God, &amp; before men, That I will not ſay ought contrary to truth or ſincerity. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath my paſſion moved me to write in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the cruelties, tho' great, which I ſuffered in the Inquiſition. The ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe of this my purpoſe, is to diſcover that deviliſh Policy, that my Reader may more clearly know it, and the more cautiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62369:5"/>it. As for my Perſon, I am a <hi>Spaniard</hi> by Birth; and with my Mothers Milk <hi>I</hi> ſuck'p in the Romiſh Religion; and at length was Ordained Prieſt. Diſcerning at laſt the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and multitude of the Superſtitions of the Roman Faction, thro' the healing influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the heavenly Illumination, I was cured, and came over to the Reformed. The Account of my Converſion, <hi>I</hi> have given in a ſmall Book, Entituled <hi>The Romiſh Prieſt Converted to the Reformed Religion. I</hi> will not therefore cloy my Reader with this; The Reformed need not my Arguments to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them, and the Papiſts will not give them a reading to convert them: moreover, ſince mens Sentiments are various, <hi>I</hi> will not much intermeddle with Doctrinals, but rather leave each one his liberty. I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe now to draw in lively Colours the <hi>Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſe</hi> of the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition;</hi> and ſo to hang it out that the well-meaning Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may be gained by it.</p>
            <p>For tho' all ſho'd know that there is a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Inquiſition,</hi> and that it is mercileſs; yet theſe very perſons may poſſibly not know the particulars which <hi>I</hi> have known, from Authors moſt worthy of Credit, and from my own experience; theſe <hi>I</hi> will briefly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to view.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62369:5"/>
            <p>The firſt occaſion of my Converſion, was the Diſagreement <hi>I</hi> ſaw among ſo many, and ſo great Divines of the Popiſh Party, in a Point whoſe certainty is judged to be that, on which the whole of our Faith doth depend. Some do much doubt the Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of a General Council; for ſo much as they ſuppoſe it doth not rely on a Divine Revelation, but (as <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam</hi> reports it) they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by a common influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aſſiſting them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Occam</hi> 9. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Tract.</hi> 3. <hi>C.</hi> 8.</note> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own Sentiment.s</p>
            <p>He farther doth peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily determine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem. Tract</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>C.</hi> 10.</note> That Pope and Cardinals are not the Rule of Faith; but if they ſhould preſume to determine any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rule of Faith contained in the Scripture, they muſt not be followed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but ought to be reprehended for it by Catholicks. Yet
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.9.5.</note> 
               <hi>Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>diſ.</hi> 1.9.1. <hi>art.</hi> 4.</note> Gregory of Arimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> and ſome others ſay, That our Faith is ultimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved into this, That that the Church is governed [They mean infallibly governed] by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62369:6"/>
            <p>On the other ſide <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſis</hi> prefers the Scriptures before the Catholick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct. fid. C.</hi> 2. <hi>Ar.</hi> 2. <hi>L.</hi> 37.</note> Catholick Biſhops, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a General Council it ſelf; and he affirms, Our Faith reſts on the Scriptures alone; ſo while <hi>I</hi> turned over their Books, <hi>I</hi> found them Combating each other; and ſaw (as <hi>Lucan</hi> words it)
<q>
                  <l>The Roman Eagles equal match'd contend,</l>
                  <l>And ſtubborn Arms each other ſtill offend.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This irreconciled War cauſed me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the doubts of the truth of Papal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. <hi>I</hi> ſaw the greateſt part of them did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve their Faith into human Opinion, while the Learnedſt, whom <hi>I</hi> read, did agree with the Reformed, as <hi>I</hi> well perceived. Thus as the more deep ſearch into every truth ordinarily ariſeth from ſome previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuſpicion; ſo my doubting was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Converſion: To the utmoſt of my power then <hi>I</hi> ſtudied, ſuſpending my aſſent from either Part; and compared each Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Cauſe and Argument with its Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, untill at length, by this means the part which the Reformed held, appeared unto
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62369:6"/>me more plain and clear.</p>
            <p>This notwithſtanding, I was ſo poſſeſſed with the Praedetermination of the Church, that I retained a ſecret doubt, whether I, who am much inferiour to many, might lawfully ſearch into theſe Controverſies. This Doubt ſtuck with me till I had certainly diſcovered the Schoolmen, allowing to every Chriſtian that judgment, which they call a Judgment of certain Knowledg, which can declare the Truth. The Reformed call it a Judgment of Diſcerning; when I had found this, I came to a calm temper, and the wavering of my mind ceaſed.</p>
            <p>I did thereupon firmly reſolve with my ſelf (ſince the Lord had enlightened my mind) to take my Journey into <hi>France,</hi> that there I might be more fully inſtructed in the Truth, and that I might renounce the Papal ſuperſtition. According to this reſolution I proceeded; and having left <hi>Spain,</hi> I tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled directly to <hi>Paris,</hi> and addreſſed my ſelf to the Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Charen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> declared my purpoſe to him, &amp; was very kindly entertained; and in this Affair I found the Reverend Monſieur <hi>D'relincourt,</hi> my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Patron, who adviſed me, ſince Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion did there run ſome hazard, I might be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62369:7"/>ſafer in <hi>Holland,</hi> whither he did (after I had, for fear of the common people, privately made my Recantation) ſend me with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Letters. So ſoon as <hi>I</hi> was come thither <hi>I</hi> went to the <hi>Hague,</hi> Saluted the Reverend and Learned Dr. <hi>Mareſius</hi> (the Son of that Eminent Profeſſour of Divinity <hi>Samuel Mareſius</hi>) who then was Miniſter in that Place, and afforded to me as much kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as could be expected from a private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and with ſingular diligence endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſet forward my Affairs; but ſeeing they ſucceeded neither as He or <hi>I</hi> had hoped, he adviſed my Return into <hi>France,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> might teach the Spaniſh Tongue, that which I would, but could not do in <hi>Holland</hi> thro' want of skill in the Dutch Tongue; my skill lay onely in the Spaniſh, Latin, Italian and French Tongues. To <hi>Paris</hi> therefore I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take my ſelf once more, &amp; lay private among the Reformed; fearing to be taken notice of by either the Seculars, or the Eccleſiaſticks in the Queens Court, where I was too well known to ſome of thoſe many Spaniards, whom the Queen (Daughter of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi>) did entertain. And what I feared long I felt too ſoon; for ſome of the Queens Domeſticks ſeized, and kept me cloſe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62369:7"/>and after a while ſent me (whether by the Queens command, or by her conſent, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not affirm) back into <hi>Spain,</hi> where I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered over to the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Eſtremadura,</hi> in the City <hi>Lerina,</hi> where after one whole years Impriſonment, weary of it, and earneſtly deſirous of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I attempted to get looſe by flight; but after I was gotten near one hundred Leagues from <hi>Lerina,</hi> and had reached the City <hi>Origne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leno,</hi> the Officers of the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> ſeized me again, and ſent me into the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> at <hi>Murcia.</hi> Here for a new Crime, which was my Eſcape from the holy <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> I was five years impriſoned, where I had neither Books, nor any Light, nor company of any man, but the bloudy <hi>Inquiſitors,</hi> and their <hi>Slaughter-men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt in an <hi>Act</hi> (as they ſpeak (<hi>of the Faith,</hi> before the <hi>Inquiſitors,</hi> the whole multitude aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embled (of whom moer hereafter) I was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the ſight of men, and to their ſcorn.</p>
            <p>The Account of my Life and fault was read before all the People; and I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and ſent away to the Gallies. The Dreſs they put me in [beſide thoſe Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it, Flames, and Pictures of Devils] I ſhall anon deſcribe. Thus immediately was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62369:8"/>I ſent to the Gallies, where they placed me, ſhaved both Head and Beard, with one foot chained, among the reſt of the Rowers. This how hard ſoever it proved, was to be my Penance. Nor do <hi>I</hi> think the Wit of <hi>Buſiris,</hi> or <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> could find out a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment more grievous, than theſe Toils are to any man unaccuſtomed to them. In the effect appeared the cruelty of their uſage, for it ſoon made me a Leper, and unfit for la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>I</hi> was extremely pined, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med away, and (which <hi>I</hi> bluſh to ſpeak) ſo great a multitude of Lice ſwarmed about me, that <hi>I</hi> might be excuſed, if <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> felt one of <hi>Egypts</hi> Plagues. And though <hi>I</hi> was kept in greateſt ſcarcity of meat and drink, which ordinarily cauſe ſweat, yet a perpetual ſweat fell from my whole Body, which [if it offend not your Ears] turned into moſt ſtinking worms, inſomuch, that oftentimes <hi>I</hi> began to think [through Satan's ſuggeſtion] That, ſeeing the many miſeries, wherewith <hi>I</hi> was viſited by the hand of God, were in manner far different from other mens, the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> had but dealt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with me. But that buffeting Meſſenger ſoon withdrew, and gave place to the divine Grace, which forthwith brought me to my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62369:8"/>remembrance, That <hi>Job</hi> a holy man had been tried with no leſs ſuffering; and this ſettled me in the belief, that theſe tryals were not penal, but Paternal Chaſtiſements, &amp; ſo <hi>I</hi> committed my ſelf and cauſe wholly to the Divine Providence, knowing that God would work for me, ſince that he hath ſaid, <hi>all things work together for good to them that love the Lord, Rom.</hi> 8. who hath at length alſo bleſt me according to mine own deſire. For all the Rowers, and others that were with me in the Gallies, earneſtly petitioned the <hi>Inquiſitor-General</hi> that he would take me out of the Gallies, were <hi>I</hi> was not onely very uſeleſs, but very hurtful, infecting others more than one way. Hereupon the <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor-General</hi> freed me from the Gallies, and confined me to the Houſe of Penance in the City <hi>Murcia,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> was handled ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely enough for ten months time; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, there at laſt <hi>I</hi> recovered, and God giving me opportunity, <hi>I</hi> once more betook my ſelf to <hi>France,</hi> and there with my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in Chriſt <hi>I</hi> renewed my Joy; yet that <hi>I</hi> might be more ſafe in praiſing God, and declaring my conſcience before men, <hi>I</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over Sea into <hi>England.</hi> This is the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of my Life, &amp; the Calamities that befel
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62369:9"/>me. And now <hi>I</hi> will give you a brief Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of that <hi>Inquiſition</hi> where <hi>I</hi> was ſo handled, and expoſe it to the view of all.</p>
            <p>This then is the Face of the Inquiſition when it proceeds to a definitive Sentence, which is paſt, as they ſpeak, in the <hi>Act of Faith.</hi> A Theatre is Erected in ſome large Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, or ſome ſuch like place; where above other Seats the Tribunal of the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> is eminent, and they attended with a Croud of Servants. Next, the Biſhop of the Place and his Chapter: Next the Magiſtrates encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with the Nobles; after all, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People follow, which flock together from all places within twenty or thirty Leagues to ſee this Solemn Act, where ſome Prieſt takes the Pulpit ſet up for the purpoſe, and in a Sermon extolls the holineſs of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> with flatteries enough; as did that Prieſt at the Act wherein <hi>I</hi> was.</p>
            <p>This Prieſt, that he might at once flatter the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and ſet forth his own Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, forged a multitude of abſurdities, and ventured to affirm;</p>
            <p>That the firſt Act of the holy <hi>Inquiſition</hi> was, that God ſolemnly inſtituted for <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt Father; thus making God the <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> that according to the cuſtom of theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62369:9"/>men under this pretence their Tyranny might be covered. And he further proſecuted his Diſcourſe, giving to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> the Name of Apoſtates, and what in him lay, making our firſt Parents Hereticks, Impenitents, and Deſerters (or Renegadoes, as we uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call ſuch) of the Faith. Now let us obſerve how this Declamation is worthy to be laught at. This Prieſt ought to have conſidered, That <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> did not totally loſe the faith and knowledg of the Lord their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour; nor did they ſin directly againſt all the Commandments of God; but in ſo much as they tranſgreſſed the Commandment of not eating the forbidden Fruit, they did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly break all. Moreover they were Elect, in whom the Act of Faith (whether general or ſpecial) might be intermitted; but the Habit could not be loſt.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Adam</hi> indeed had become wholly an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolater, if he had wholly departed from the Faith, and Profeſſion of the moſt high God, This declaiming Prieſt might have had ſmoe colour for what he ſaid: But ſince <hi>Adam</hi> was not ſuch, the reaſoning of the Prieſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in a falſehood; and his Allegory could be nothing better than helliſh, whileſt he condemns the Sin as Hereſie, and the Perſon as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62369:10"/>Apoſtate, without any reſpect to the honour, God in Creating, had put upon him, making him the King and Lord of the whole World. Yet the Allegory is more ridiculous, in which the Prieſt brings in God Supream Lord of all us, as <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> and ſo advanceth their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitor</hi> to an abſolute Supremacy; whereas all know, that the <hi>Inquiſitor</hi> General is ſubject to the Pope.</p>
            <p>Further, Paradiſe is made the Theatre of Hereſies, on which God is ſuppoſed to have the information brought in by the Accuſers, and to pronounce Sentence when all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances had been conſidered; but here who ſhall be the Officers? Good Angels were not made for this. And ſuch honour was too great for Devills who might indeed be the Executioners, but not Aſſiſtants in the courſe of Judgment. He might as well have added, that our Protoplaſts thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, were delivered over to that Angel, who had the flaming Sword put into his hand, that he might be Armed as well to Execute them, as to keep the entrance into Paradiſe. So one abſurdity naturally ariſeth out of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; and who chooſeth to utter one, may canly iſivent an hundred fond Conceits. With
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62369:10"/>ſuch a ſtore as this furniſht, he did the beſt he could in finiſhing his Allegory; and that he might neatly flatter the Fathers, Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of that <hi>Inquiſition;</hi> he tells them, that God clothed our firſt Parents with the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious Veſt, the San-benita juſt like theirs, which by their command the condemned Hereticks were clad with.</p>
            <p>And in doing this, the Prieſt was very pleaſantly ridiculous; He like an excellent Brother turns the skins, with which God co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the nakedneſs of our firſt Parents, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to San-benita's. An ungrounded and Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Allegory, without any reſemblance! for the San-benita is an open expoſing of the Perſon to ſhame; the skins were to cover the ſhame of the perſons that wore them. So the skins leſſened the ſhame, and were given out of mercy; the San-benita aggravated the ſhame, and were impoſed by ſevere revenge.</p>
            <p>Certainly <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> owe little to this Prieſt, who when he ought to treat them with all Veneration, as became the Head and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Mankind, when he ſhould have owned a good hope of their Salvation, in as much as they were the firſt fruits of both Church and State; he recounts them He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, and as ſuch treats them; he brands
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62369:11"/>them as final Apoſtates; makes Paradiſe a Theatre for Renegado's, and brings our firſt Fathers on it as ſpreaders of Heretical Infection, clothes them with the <hi>Sanbenita,</hi> pronounceth final Sentence againſt them; and whether God will or no, this bold Prieſt will make him <hi>Inquiſitor</hi> General; but in very deed we have cauſe to doubt whether this Prieſt were a Deſcendent from them in right Line; or whether of the Brood of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, that he durſt ſpit out that venome againſt Paradiſe, by this moſt unjuſt Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, of which the Devil himſelf would nigh be aſhamed. But theſe and ſuch like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing Parallels and unſhapen Similitudes, are invented and publiſhed in the Kingdom of <hi>Spain,</hi> which would be happy enough, were it well rid of ſuch venomous Beaſts.</p>
            <p>Yet in the abundance of this Prieſts Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and vanity, he declares that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Holy, and proves it, becauſe it retains the Holy Tribunal of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and defends it, as if indeed the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> did with moderation manage the Government; as if it gave freedom of defence, and did no injury to the Innocent; as if its rigor did not exceed what wholeſome care did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ect towards the accuſed; when as quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62369:11"/>that Tribneal is moſt juſtly had in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination by all people.</p>
            <p>It calls it ſelf Holy, but is pure Tyranny, and a very great ſcandal to Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and Commonwealths; while they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be the Pillar of the Faith, they are the Wrack of the Faithful. So that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Tyrannical Effects of, it we may well wonder, that it is continued to this day in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I wiſh they would tell me, what kind of Judgment-ſeat that is, which admits not a Priſoner, ſometimes for ten or twelve years together to appear before them, and to plead his Cauſe, which mean time will not allow any perſon to converſe with the Priſoner, beſide the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> and the Keeper of the Priſon? What Juſtice does that Tribunal miniſter, which refuſeth to let the Accuſed know the Names of thoſe that witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him?</p>
            <p>What Righteouſneſs in that Government, where Chriſtian Piety caſt off, they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all their Goods and Poſſeſſions, the labour of many years, who cannot be proved guilty of any fault, but of errour of mind? when by the divine allowance, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> witneſſeth, is, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3. <hi>That man ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62369:12"/>ſee the good of his labour all his days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Juſtice or honour does that Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men retain, which denies natural right to women and children; that puts the ſhameful San-benita on thoſe of moſt Noble Families, and overthrows whole Families at once? I will take leave to divert, for proof of what I have ſaid, to the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> where, with cruelties greater than which <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> firſt uſed, they condemn to death, never acquainting the Condemned with either number, or names of Witneſſes; Thus they manage it; Firſt they apprehend a man as a Jew, or Mahumetan, or Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, thruſt him into Priſon, without telling him who, or how many accuſe him: Next he ſuffers the miſeries of this Impriſonment ſix or eight, or ten years; if at laſt the man, to get out of their hands, confeſſeth all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed againſt him to be true; and implores (what they never ſhew) their mercy; then the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> proceed to enquire whether he knew his Accuſers. The poor man [as is truth] anſwers he knows them not; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon [though he confeſs, and ſue for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy] yet he is burnt, becauſe he knows nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons, nor names of his Accuſers. Here oftentimes it happens, that the man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62369:12"/>cauſe he will not die unrevenged, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out company, accuſeth a whole Village or Town, that amongſt them he may hit the Perſons that accuſed; O degenerate Age! O barbarous Cuſtoms. <hi>Can Chriſtians find ſuch</hi> Inquiſitors, <hi>when the Heathens never would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch?</hi> Where was ſuch irregular cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ever acted elſewhere, ſince God Created <hi>Adam</hi> in the Field of <hi>Meſopotamia?</hi> Let us turn over divine and human Hiſtories, we ſhall find none ſorcruel. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ruled with rigour, but 'twas to finiſh his Buildings. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſuerus</hi> promoted <hi>Haman;</hi> for want of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from a ſingle perſon, a cruel revenge was deſigned againſt the Life of all the Jews; yet this Decree paſt openly, not in private. <hi>Balthazar</hi> prophanely abuſed the holy Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, but did not cruelly murther the people of God. <hi>Antiochus</hi> perſecuted the Jews; yet heard their Cauſe in a publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> and other Tyrants vexed the people by Arms. <hi>Nero</hi> and other Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperours appointed publick Priſons, and invented divers kinds of death for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: yet theſe all exerciſed their Tyranny with an open proceſs in the ſight of the world.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62369:13"/>
            <p>But no where is there found a Tribunal like to the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition:</hi> every wiſe man can't but condemn this as moſt directly deſtructive to human nature, and to all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which requires a fair and publick Tryal; and where the Cauſe is puniſhable proportions the puniſhment to the Crime, with ſome reſpect to the frailty of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders puniſhed. Furthermore I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire leave to ask,</p>
            <p>What honour the Roman Profeſſion gains by theſe Acts of Faith, which are ſolemnized in <hi>Spain?</hi> wherein is the righteouſneſs of that Religion they call Catholick? Do the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſee, or ſo much as know their Accuſers? Nay, do they know their Crime which they ſhould clear themſelves of? Have they leave to conſult an Advocate in the Priſon? or to ask Counſel of any prudent men, and zealous in faith; who might on examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inſtruct them that erre, and comfort them that are innocent? May, the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner though for eight or ten years together enjoy the light of the Sun; or ever knew how the Affairs of his Family are managed? Nothing of all this! ſo that 'tis no inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to conclude againſt theſe unexemplified Tyrants, That they break and violate all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62369:13"/>the Laws of kindneſs, truth and humanity. They do pretend an abſolute power granted to them; though this be againſt all Law divine and human; <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. It is God onely hath right to ſuch a Power; He one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can exerciſe it without putting us into tormenting fear, that any future injuſtice ſhall ever be done againſt us, or any of the Creatures. The Righteouſneſs of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is owned in the Book of <hi>Job,</hi> where you have an excellent Theological Diſcourſe on the exact Righteouſnes of the Creator; and the narrow conceptions of the Creature Man. In the bitterneſs of his Soul <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, when he ſaith to God, <hi>Job</hi> 10.2. <hi>Donot contemn me; ſhew me the reaſon why thou contendeſt with me?</hi> As if with <hi>David</hi> he would ſay, why doeſt thou enter into judgment with me? what need God to juſtifie his way before man? His ways are the abſolute <hi>Idea</hi> of Juſtice. He may work as he will; we muſt reverence the Workman: Thy Judgments, O God, are very juſt; we muſt believe it, and not pry into them; They exceed man's reach, and are cloathed with moſt deep Myſteries, yet it is corrective, not deſtructive of us. This Abſolute Authority impudent <hi>Inquiſitors</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62369:14"/>would uſurp, and relying on this erroneous Opinion, <hi>Nimrod</hi>-like, they hunt for the Goods, Bodies, and Lives of Men.</p>
            <p>Now that the abſoluteneſs of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings may more evidently appear, (kind Reader) I will prove by divers inſtances, that without ever looking into, or debating of the Cauſe, they have moſt tyrannically condemned the Perſon. Though the thing itſelf prove this enough, for the Inquiſition-Court is ſubject to no direction of any other Laws, but arbitrarily wracks Souls, and murthers Bodies, of which there are Clouds of Witneſſes, men Condemned, becauſe the Inquiſition would be cruel. Good God! that ever this Tribunal ſhould pretend to a Divine Impulſe, where every Brick ſeems a Conjuring Spell, and every Officer a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Fiend; for ſuppoſe we a Jew, a Mahumetan, or Chriſtian in their Paws, what do they pretend to do with ſuch a one? Would they chaſtiſe him? what need they then ſo many Officers? why ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods extremely ſcandalous, as a ſecret Chamber, an unſeen Tribunal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inviſible Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, a perfidious Secretary, and mercileſs Servants, Confiſcation of Goods through fraud and guile, Keepers as hard-hearted as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62369:14"/>the relentleſs Walls, the Fiſcal Mutes, the ſhameful Sambenites, a deaf Audient, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Wracks, a Theatre fill'd with horrour to aſtoniſh the Priſoner, a ſentence with Hypocriſie, a diſguized Executioner, and finally a peremptory Judgment. In all the times of Paganiſm no ſuch <hi>Roman</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal was ever erected. In their Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theaters men had not quite put off Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the guilty and condemned to die were expoſed to wild Beaſts to be torn in pieces; they knew their Executioner, but here the Condemned are tormented by diſguiz'd ones: Men they ſhould be by their ſhape, but Devils by their fierceneſs and cruelty.</p>
            <p>Theſe General Acts of the Faith are no where acted, but in the greater Cities of the Kingdom; and the ordering of them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents thee Reader with a ſight of both the fooliſh madneſs, and helliſh fury of a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Generation of men. For obſerve,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Keepers of the Priſon drag their Priſoners ignominiouſly attired with the <hi>Sambenito,</hi> and a Mitre (called <hi>Coroza</hi> by the Vulgar;) Next flock together (beſides the above-named) the Univerſity men; thoſe they call Familiars, or Serjeants of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, follow next; then the Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62369:15"/>Qualificators, Notaries of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Secretaries, and the Fiſcals, with the whole croud of common people, come together (as I ſaid before) from twenty or thirty Leagues about; to theſe muſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Legion, compleatly armed, with their Standard, the Green Croſs, carried before them, and there with a Canopy of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Ells of Linnen to caſt a ſhade over the Inquiſitors, and the Nobles; in the midſt of the Theatre an Altar is ſet up, and about that all the Pariſh Prieſts, the Officials, and the Hangman: I do ſcarce think that any of thoſe four Monarchies (the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian, Grecian,</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi>) which once rul'd the World, ever appointed ſuch great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance of ſo many Officers to execute a Sentence on twenty or thirty poor men. Who that knows this, can reſtrain his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, grief and pity, to ſee this Calamity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen the Age, Tyranny holding the place of Juſtice? Who would not ſue to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Life, that he would ſhew that Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Grace to the Age, that the darkneſs being diſpell'd, this barbarous cruelty might ceaſe, which hitherto hath not been ſatisfied with depriving innocent men of their whole Eſtates, with forcing them to own what they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62369:15"/>never did, but hath proceeded to an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Execution, applauded by that Scum of the people which follow it. Oh inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Age! old in Cruelty, but very raw and ungrown in Vertue! But I come (as I promiſed) to give you an Hiſtorical Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome Caſes brought under the <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of this Judgment-Seat, by which you may ſee the Equity of that they call Moſt Holy, which on a Moral probability con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and execute, nay on a meer ſuſpition they'l do it.</p>
            <p>In the City of <hi>Toledo,</hi> 1644. they dragg'd upon this infamous Theatre, <hi>Dominicus de Monteſines, Franciſcus de Cacetes, Franciſous Vaſquez, Lewis de Valencia, Emmanuel Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zales,</hi> each bearing a Green Wax Candle in their hand, and fined each of ehem four thouſand Crowns; and if you would know the cauſe, it was meerly through ſuſpition, foraſmuch as they were of a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Race: for this they were forced under this diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to pay the debts they never owed. Should we enquire, we could not find a Law temper'd with any ſound reaſon, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judgeth men to torments on ſuch ſlight ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition; God himſelf, Supreme Judge, in the caſe of that Theft by <hi>Achan</hi> committed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62369:16"/>at <hi>Jericho,</hi> directs <hi>Joſhua</hi> to ſind out and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the perſon by lot, when God Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient could have told who was the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: But by ſuch ordinary courſe, in ſight of all the people, God will have the buſinefs decided, to remove all ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>In the ſame year and City aforeſaid <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius de Vega</hi> was brought forth, his caſe is ridiculous enough, and as will appear, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves not our pity, becauſe of his own fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in it: But let's tell the injuſtice of the <hi>Inquiſition.</hi> This fooliſh man, when at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, went on his own accord, accuſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he once was of the Opinion that a man might be ſaved by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and that for ſome time he had obſerved it, but through the Grace of God enlightned, he acknowledged his errour, was come to confeſs his ſins at the footſtool of their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, and to ſue for Abſolution by the Judges of the Holy Inquiſition. Now though this action was voluntary, and deſerved forgiveneſs; yet, as in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proverb, 'tis confeſs and be hang'd. So was <hi>Fernandes</hi> firſt caſt into ſecret Priſon, and after three years detainure in Priſon, to bewail his ſin, the Judgment paſt againſt him to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of all his Goods, the attiring him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62369:16"/>with the <hi>Sambenito,</hi> putting the Green Candle into his hand, and ſo to be brought into the Theatre: unutterable inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! What words can expreſs this Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? Exclamations are too little to raiſe our wonder and indignation.</p>
            <p>In the City <hi>Lerino,</hi> there were two Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Mother <hi>Major de Luna,</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Antonia,</hi> who after they had confeſſed (whether truly or falſly is uncertain) forced thereto by the torments thoſe Executioners put them to, were drawn into the Theatre with Green Candles (as condemned) in their hands, their Goods Conſiſcated, the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whipt with one hundred ſtripes, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with two hundred through the Streets; [This was done after they had been kept ſix years in Priſon] &amp; now 1652 both after theſe extreme rigours condemned to a perpetual impriſonment.</p>
            <p>In the year 1639. in the Town, <hi>Alcazar de Conſuegra,</hi> among other rich Families, one there was, whoſe Chief Head above the reſt was a certain man, by name <hi>de Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Eſcuſa,</hi> a Jew by deſcent from thoſe which had eſcap't the cruelty of the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition.</hi> Now ſo it happen'd, that near to the Palace of the ſaid <hi>de Villa Eſcuſa,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62369:17"/>a certain Maid, an Orphan, by the death of both her Parents, with three Brethren, the Eldeſt of which was not full ſix years old; this Maid was of Chriſtian Patents, and over-much deſired Marriage with that Noble Rich Man, Lord of the place, but he refus'd to Marry her that was Poor, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would he burthen himſelf with her three Brothers, and anſwer'd thoſe that courted him to the Match, that had ſhe not three Brothers, he would have Married her. When the Virgin perceived her ſelf refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and diſappointed of a great Match, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had Brothers, ſhe (mad with Love) reſolved to kill the Children, and to throw them into the Well, out of which the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>de Villa Eſcuſa</hi> drew water for their houſhold uſes. This devilliſh reſolution ſhe did put into practice one night, and cut off the Heads of her own three Brethren, and threw them into that Well: After a while, the Neighbours miſſing the Children, with great out-cry reſolved to ſearch for them through the whole Town and Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: While this was doing, a Smith (who lived over-right <hi>de Villa Eſcuſa</hi>'s Houſe) with three Rogues more, entered diſcourſe among themſelves, and confidently affirm'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62369:17"/>the Children kill'd by the <hi>Jews</hi> for Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, [ſuch are the reaſonings of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Vulgar] forthwith they go to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticer of the place, who took their Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but perceiving it proceeded of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice would meddle no more in it. The Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers perceiving this, addreſſed themſelves to the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and declared their moſt wicked thoughts; and affirmed on Oath, that <hi>De Villa Eſcuſa</hi> had murthered the Children, was alſo a Jew, that at twelve at Night they heard the Children crying in <hi>De Villa Eſcuſa</hi>'s houſe. [but the Cry was in the houſe of the Siſter of the Children] They ſwear alſo that the Boys were ſeen to go into <hi>Villa Eſcuſa</hi>'s houſe late at Night, but none ever ſaw them come out. As for proof, that <hi>Villa Eſcuſa</hi> was a Jew, they knew it they ſaid, becauſe they had ſeen him put on his ſhirt on Saturday; a mad proof, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the madder, and more unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> which could take this that had the leaſt ſuſpicion poſſible, and make it the Ground of tormenting the Innocent; like the Wolf that quartell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Lamb for fouling the water. The innocent <hi>De Villa Eſcuſa</hi> is ſeized, his Well ſearched, where at laſt they found the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62369:18"/>murthered Children. He is put to the Wrack, where not able to bear the pain, he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all true of which he was accuſed; that he had murthered the Children, that he was a Jew, a Mahumetan, a Lutheran, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they would have him to be; after this Confeſſion, his Goods are confiſcated, and attired with the <hi>Sambenito,</hi> he is carried and delivered to the Secular Power, which took care that he ſhould that very day be hanged and quartered. At the Gallows this poor man proteſted, that being unable to bear the pains of the Wrack, he had owned as done by him what he never had done; and this he avowed upon his Death</p>
            <p>The Inhabitants of the Place do now jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vially feaſt and rejoyce at the death of this poor man, and load his Kindred with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſgrace; but after two years the Siſter Murthereſs, diſappointed of her hoped Match, went to <hi>Toledo</hi> to Confeſſion, and there confeſſed the Fact, from which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor would not abſolve her till ſhe had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent great penance; which when ſhe had endured for one whole moneth, one Morning cloathed with Sackcloth, and her Head covered with Aſhes, and girded about with many Cords, ſhe comes abroad, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62369:18"/>publickly, with a loud voice, before the people, cries out that ſhe had killed her Brother, to the end ſhe might marry that Noble Perſonage: That <hi>De Villa Eſcuſa</hi> was inocent, and ſuffered wrongfully; that ſhe declared this to appeaſe and quiet her Conſcience. Now a certain Kinſman, of the Dead <hi>Villa Eſcuſa,</hi> was preſent, who brought her before the Judg of that Place; by whom after ſhe had confeſſed the Fact ſhe was adjudged to be hanged; and the four Witneſſes being well whipped, were condemned to the Gallies. Thus poor <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Eſcufa</hi> died by the Judgment of that Court; which notwithſtanding their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to a guidance by an infallible ſpirit, are by this very Fact convinced that this is but a pretence; That the Spirit which acts them, is that Spirit which is a Murtherer, and was ſo from the Beginning.</p>
            <p>In the year 1658, there came abroad in <hi>Portugal</hi> another Nero, one <hi>Simon de Mene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Inquiſitor</hi> at <hi>Coimbra,</hi> whoſe miſchiefs were as many as a whole Legion of Fiends could have wrought. This man invented unuſual ways, to make Priſoners confeſs, and by a Graft, brought from Hell, he got the the Names of all: and made many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62369:19"/>(whether they would or no) to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Jews; many of theſe were ſuch Chriſtians in heart, not onely in word, that they were condemned, and executed onely becauſe they would not own themſelves to be Jews. So great was the barbarbus cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this bloudy man, that having appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended one <hi>Vaz,</hi> born at <hi>Porta,</hi> and married to <hi>Anna de Lujan,</hi> (both perſons of mean a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities) he compelled them both to confeſs by the threats he uſed againſt them; who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous of liberty, and to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from this Monſter, they accuſed all they new, not ſparing the Abbeys and Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries, for they accuſed two Religious of noble Quallty: Now, becauſe he might not apprehend any of ſuch noble Family, unleſs two Witneſſes in one place, at one time, did witneſs in the Caſe: This Officer of <hi>Belzebub</hi> brought <hi>Vaz</hi> and his Wife into one Chamber, and there taught them the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d how they ſhould proceed in accuſing and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing the Accuſed to be guilty; and in one day theſe perſons brought into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſeventy perſons, all of them Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of that City. And whereas the <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fition</hi> never gives the Names of the Accuſers but leaves the Priſoners to conjecture at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62369:19"/>them: This curſed <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> with a ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (that became ſo great an Impoſtor) would place four or ſix perſons in the Entry of that Houſe, through which the Priſoner was to go, that thereby the Priſoner might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured to ſpeak with them, of whom when the Priſoner (thinking they were in like Caſe with himſelf, though they were Trepanners) did ask where the <hi>Inquiſitor</hi> was, and who with him? One or other of thoſe infamous Fellows would name the Chamber, and ſay ſuch or ſuch (that the <hi>Inquiſitor</hi> would have them name, though 'twere Father or Mother of the Accuſed) were with the <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> by whom the Accuſed was betrayed, and ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all his Goods: if this did not ſucceed, This Atheiſtical <hi>Inquiſitor</hi> would come with Alas! Brother I pray you own your ſelf guilty, though you know you are not; for unleſs you do thus, there is no remedy, you will be burnt; and if this prevailed not, he preſently made uſe of Tortures, to force the confeſſion he could not perſwade; and thus he ruined many innocent Ones. Once he apprehended one <hi>Emanuel de Coſta,</hi> a man of good Note, who was Husband to <hi>Cateli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Doza,</hi> Kinswoman to this <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> who calling <hi>Emanuel</hi> to him one day, tells him
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62369:20"/>he is ſorry he hath married his Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, who will (ſaih he) bring your Soul to the Devil; and withall adviſeth him to confeſs, and truſt him with his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit which ſhould be preſerved, and he ſhould not be brought on the Theatre, nor his Goods ſeized: The poor <hi>Acoſta</hi> anſwers, I have been, and ſtill am a Chriſtian, and what can I confeſs? ſaith the <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> though thou art not, yet ſeem in confeſſion to be guilty, and truſt me with your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Bewitched with the words of the <hi>Inquiſitor;</hi> This miſerable man confeſſeth ſo as to condemn perſons that were ſtrangers to him, whoſe Names this <hi>Simon (Magus)</hi> had given to <hi>Acoſta,</hi> and by this wile very many were apprehended.</p>
            <p>In the end <hi>Acoſta</hi> perceiving the <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor's</hi> promiſes were without effect, he pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned to be heard, and recants all that he had before confeſſed, proteſting he was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> to give falſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, under promiſe of a reſtitution to his honour and liberty: But here <hi>Meneſes</hi> ſo managed the matter, That <hi>Acoſta</hi> muſt either recant his Recantation, or burn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy, <hi>Acoſta</hi> not daring the latter, choſe the former, and ſo by loſs of fame
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62369:20"/>and Goods ſaved his Life. <hi>Meneſes</hi> had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other miſchievous method which he often uſed; when a Priſoner had been eight years, ſometimes more than ten, he would bring him before their Tribunal; (though 'twere evident the perſon was innocent) and thus beſpeak the Secretary, (with greateſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs, and with equal hypocriſie) Mr. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary,</hi> appoint an Act, in which you may declare the perſon before to be one that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats not the mercy of this our holy Court, who as often as invited to confeſs his fault, ſo often, (notwithſtanding mercy offered him) repeats his denial, and ſeems to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign dying in his own Errour: To this the Secretary (with great Hypocriſie) anſwers, <hi>Sir,</hi> will you that this miſerable man ſhould thus die? have you ſhut the door againſt all mercy towards him? I pray you give him three days ſpace to acknowledg his own fault, and the juſtice of this Court: By this Contrivance, between the <hi>Inquiſitor</hi> and the Secretary, they take the Perſon for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and convicted; ſo they have ruined innumerable men, and ſpoiled them of Life and Eſtate.</p>
            <p>In the year 1650. The Secretary of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> his Name <hi>Paroda,</hi> came from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62369:21"/>
               <hi>Quenſa</hi> to <hi>Paſtrana;</hi> bringing with him a cheating Knave for apprehending ſome they call Hereticks, but indeed innocent perſons, by Authority from the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of <hi>Quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa;</hi> empowring them to ſeize as many as that Cheat ſhould name. Now, on a certain Night the Officers (called <hi>Familiars</hi>) with the Secretary went out in Queſt for their Prey, and entred a Street which led to the Market-place, accompanied with the Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panner, whoſe face was covered; Thus the Secretary came to a Shop of a certain Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueſe, (for at that time there was a Mart at <hi>Paſtrana,</hi> to which the Inhabitants of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Towns did come) and commanded him to open his doors; whom by an Arreſt, in the Name of their (moſt holy) <hi>Inquiſition</hi> he ſeized, which was done by the Officers, the Signal being given by bowing down the Head, when they ſhould ſeize; and lifting up the Head when they were to forbear ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing; that very Night forty two Perſons were ſeized; and whileſt they were kept cloſe in the Houſes of thoſe Familiars; the Secretary, falſe Witneſs, with the reſt of the Robbers at Midnight, return to the Shops, and take away as much as they could carry; which in money and Wares amounted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62369:21"/>to twenty thouſand Crowns and upward.</p>
            <p>Now, when they ſhould have carried theſt Priſoners to <hi>Quenſa</hi> they diſmiſſed them all but one, whom they carried to <hi>Quenſa,</hi> where they gave him an admonition, and ſet him at liberty; but the money, being the Heretick they ſought after they never let go out of their hands. And though this Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery was known, and ſufficiently proved, yet the righteous <hi>Inquiſitors,</hi> neither puniſhed Secretary nor Witneſs, giving this reaſon for their lenity, That without Accuſers there would be no Priſoners; and without theſe no <hi>Inquiſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1660. At <hi>Liſbone</hi> an Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant boldly went into the Temple, and took the Hoaſt from the place, where it was kept, and departed forthwith for <hi>England,</hi> the next day the Curate of the Church miſſing the Hoaſt, publiſhed abroad the miſhap; the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> beſtirs it ſelf: and its Officers affirm, that without doubt the Jews had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it away; therefore they diligently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire who of the Jews were that Night ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from their own houſe, at laſt they came to the houſe of a young man of ſix and twenty years of Age, and Maſter of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd thouſand Crowns; his Name <hi>Solis;</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62369:22"/>They examine the Servants whether their Maſter were at home at that Night, who told the truth he was not; (for indeed that Night taken up with the criminal delights of his youth, he ſpent with a certain Lady of good Quality, that was Eſpouſed [at leaſt betrothed] to a Gentleman of no mean Rank) When <hi>Solis</hi> heard their charge againſt him, he confeſſed he was abſent that Night from home, but that he ſpent it with a Lady, whoſe name he would not tell, though he died for it; yet under the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Wrack he told the Houſe where he was, though not the perſon with whom he was; Thither the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> haſte, but either could not, or elſe would not ſtir far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Affair, becauſe the Lady was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the common ſize; or becauſe they had the man, by whom they were ſure to find, what they hunted, the hundred thouſand Caowns. They return therefore to the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing of the young man, who is forced to own he took away the Hoaſt, and had eaten it; This done, his Goods are confiſcated; he is condemned to be burnt, but firſt his hands muſt be cut off. When the hour of Execution was come, the Haugman deſired him to put forth his right hand, which he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62369:22"/>with an undaunted mind did, ſaying, <hi>I give up this for my Lord Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who knows I never committed any ſuch fault, but forced by the ſeverity of the Wrack, and allured by the promiſes of the <hi>Inquiſitors,</hi> who ſaid they would ſave my Life, <hi>I</hi> did unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y confeſs what <hi>I</hi> never did act: Then they lout off his other hand, and burned him in the ſight of the people, who made a great Feaſt, in token that they approved what was none by thoſe incarnate Devils. After this was done the Engliſhman wrote into <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> to them, letting them know he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away their Breaden God, on purpoſe to expoſe both it and the Papal Religion to that ſcorn they deſerved. But <hi>Solis</hi> fell by the moſt pious <hi>Inquiſition!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1656, in the City <hi>Lerina,</hi> a certain French Man that got his Living by ſelling up and down the Streets Knives, Ciſſars, Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and Girdles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> like ſmall Wares, was ſeized by the <hi>Inquiſition;</hi> The occaſion of which was this, An Image of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> was one morning found torn in the Corner of a certain Street, where 'twas ſet that people might do it honour; now on the over-night, this Frenchman paſſing by, at that place met ſome of his Acquaintance,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62369:23"/>who were <hi>Caſtilians,</hi> who ſaluted him, and he them, and ſo went on to his Lodging, as they did to theirs: next day the Magiſtrate ſeeing the Image broken, made a diligent ſearch, and theſe <hi>Caſtilians</hi> Friends (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enemies) of the French Man, affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he had broken the Image, for they ſaw him the Night before near unto it. This one of the Familiars (as Setter for the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors</hi>) heard of, accuſed him before their Tribunal, and ſwears to what he affirmed. The poor French Man is clapt up into Priſon, pleads for himſelf that he went to his Friends houſe, where he played at Cards all the while, which appeared to be true upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry; yet was he detained, for ſo much as his Acquaintance ſwore he was an Heretick; (which is the common name they give the <hi>Reformed</hi>) And ſo cruelly handled that the pain he ſuffered, forced him to ſay he was <hi>reformed,</hi> and had given ſeveral blows to the Image, and that for this he did beg par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, which was granted to him as he was Proteſtant; but becauſe he did offer an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity to the Image, he is condemned to the fire, and ſuffered the extremity of that Judgment. Now about two moneths after, a certain Fool, who had lived at <hi>Lerina,</hi> but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62369:23"/>was removed to an Habgation two miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, was ſound in the night thruſting down another Image which was newly ſet up in the room of the former; him they exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whether he had broken the former, and he owned it, ſaying, He intended to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it to his Farm where he had built a ſmall Chappel; to this he added ſome other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d tricks, by which the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> was aſſured of the <hi>French-mans</hi> Innocency, yet acquitted the Witneſſes as if they had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the truill, and as if the <hi>French man</hi> had died for his own Crime.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Madril, An.</hi> 1663. fell out an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Caſe, which was as follows, The Son of a certain Woman, named <hi>Marqueſa,</hi> was Debtor to a certain new Chriſtian (as they call newly converted Jews) in a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſum of Money, which either he could not, or would not pay. Like a Fury of Holl he ſets his malice on work, and wiltes in great Letters this following ſentence; <hi>It is meet they ſhould live, who love according to the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>it is fit they ſhould die, who live after the Laws of Chriſt,</hi> and affixeth it to the doors of a place called <hi>Quadralactura,</hi> where a great concourſe of people uſually meet; and to increaſe the number, the next
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62369:24"/>day he cauſed a great tumult, which did juſtly offend the Court of Juſtice; which iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out an Order for the Juſtice to make extraordinary ſearch into the thing: The Inquiſition did their part, yet for three Months the ſecret lay hid, but then ſome found this Villain with ſuch Scrowls, both for their tenure, and for the hand the very ſame, and having ſeiz'd him, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfeſt that out of preconceiv'd hatred againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> he had done it, to inflame the people againſt them to their ruine. Now though he deſerved to ſuffer what he would have brought on others, yet this Juſt Inquiſition adjudgeth him but to one hundred ſtripes; the reaſon of which was, he was a Papiſt againſt whom he had deviſed it, whereas had the accuſed been of other Religion, he who was Accuſer, right or wrong, ſhould have been Credited, and the Accuſed ſhould have died for it. More Caſes <hi>I</hi> ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to recount, becauſe I would not be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious; yet, let me add this paſſage of an Inquiſitor in the City <hi>Quenca,</hi> his name <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovic, de le Torre,</hi> who was uſed to beſpeak the Priſoners thus; <hi>Friends, you were as good corfeſs as not, for if once you come into the hands of the Inquiſition, you ſhall never get
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62369:24"/>out: There are Tortures, an Executioner, and Graves for all that will not confeſs, and there is Wood enough to burn all that do confeſs.</hi> Hence 'tis clear to every one what Spirit doth act the Spaniſh Inquiſition, which by Examples Hiſtorically we have reproved hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto: now ſet me demonſtrate dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally their injuſtice: Though the thing require a greater and more prudent judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet I will endeavour to demonſtrate what I have undertaken.</p>
            <p>There is not one Law in the World which ought not be built upon Reaſon, which as it adorns the Law, ſo allures men both to the ſtudy of it, and to the Veneration of it, for the Reaſon of the Law is as the Lond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, an Attractive to our enquity, our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, and our obſervance, ſo far the Judge, the Court, and Witneſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſacred, as the Law which directs them is rational; ſo would the Tribunal of the Inquiſition be what they call it, were Reaſon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Laws; and proceedings which they manage by thoſe Laws, but all with them is far from this; yet three things they pretend in the very Title they aſſume, which is the <hi>Holy Office of Inquiſition,</hi> the firſt part is, 'tis Holy, (ſay theſe unholy Murtherers;)
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62369:25"/>it is then Divine, and their work muſt be Divine, which whether it be or no, let us now enquire; what is Divine doth primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt in what is ſpiritual, in things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, which are great myſteries, and which cannot be known Scientifically, nor compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by Natural Reaſon: Were this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal thus Divine, it would omit nothing of what it could do to inform men in the way of Salvation, and to open to them the ſecret myſteries of Gods Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: But all their buſineſs really is to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mens ſecrets, for ruining their Eſtates, and diſſeiſing the owner, that [<hi>Ahab</hi>-like] they may ſeize all. Farther, were this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal holy, it would approve, chuſe, and promote holineſs, as God doth; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth holineſs to the righteous, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it in them, and exerciſeth them thereunto. Now where is ought of this to be found, either in the cruel diſpoſition, or injurious proceedings of this Court, and its Officers? Where you find the greateſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and moſt of the Devils malice, there is nothing Divine, or of God; there holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is condemned, and the holy are burnt, though ſometimes they condemn a vile Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, yet they never abſolve a known
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62369:25"/>Saint, a Lover of Chriſt and Truth; and were it holy, it would reſemble the holyneſs of him in his Created State under the Law of Nature. But here is nothing of that where all the Laws of natural equity and compaſſion are violated, by Forgery againſt the innocent, by forcing them to ſhorten their preſent torments by owning faults they never committed; in ſhort, uſing all, ſo as none of them would be uſed by other. Here is nothing divine, natural; nor is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in this Tribunal any conformity to the honneſs which ſhines forth in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the beſt methods of Government, and beſt provided for ſafety of Innocents. This <hi>Inquiſition</hi> is the moſt pernicious to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents, wearing out with long impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thoſe that retain their Innocency, and burning thoſe that forego it to pleaſe the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors. Moſes</hi>'s Law was holy, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>to love mercy, do juſtice, and walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with God.</hi> The <hi>Inquiſitors,</hi> for pride, like Lucifer, for injuſtice unparallelled, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious abhorrers of mercy: Say Reader whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Tribunal can be holy and divine? There is one more holy Tribunal, which is that of Grace, which to ſave life, not to deſtroy it, And well doth the Tribunal
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62369:26"/>of <hi>Inquiſition</hi> correſpond to this, doth it not? which is ſet up to deſtroy life, not to ſave it. On Chriſt's Throne is written Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but on the <hi>Inquiſitor's</hi> Death and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; but yet it is a Judgment-ſeat, and hath a great authority, and therefore divine. Indeed, were it of God, it were divine, but it is of the Pope, an Uſurper, a Tyrant, a bloudy cruel one; and theſe <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by him, are to execute his bloudy deſigns on all innocent ones accuſed, and brought within their ſnare; God permits, and abhors it now; and as he hath puniſhed many, ſo he will puniſh all the reſt of this bloudy Crew which prophane the venerable names of faith, juſtice and holineſs, with their Robberies, Murthers and Perjuries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us view how juſtly they claim to be an Office. This is an authority exerciſed for directing, protecting, and encouraging, without partiality, every one in the duty he owes to others, and to the publick, in thoſe things which fall under the Rule of that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: It ſuperviſeth the work of every one who owes any duty to it: and it is founded in one of thoſe three Laws we before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; and ſo is either natural, political, or ſpiritual.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:62369:26"/>
            <p>The Natural is governed by that Maxim, whatſoever thou wouldeſt not ſhould be done to thee, do not thou to others. The Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal is regulated by what is conductive to the tranquillity and ſafety of life: The Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al employs it ſelf in a care for welfare of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſouls. Theſe Offices have been by Learned Men cleared and commended in their proper places, of which I ſhall not now ſpeak. The <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> pretend not that their Court and Rules of it are <hi>Moſaic;</hi> poſſibly they may conjecture they are depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this Office by Law of Nature; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are deceived, for this Office is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where; nor do they as they would be done to; nor is it ſpiritual or Evangelical; for it takes not care of the ſalvation of ſouls, and to acquaint them with the Doctrine of the Goſpel; For let it be conſidered,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who ſo is appointed to this Office ought to hear the Offender, and to treat him according to the Talent entruſted to him in Spirituals; and if the underſtanding be darkned, he ſhould as a ſpiritual Phyſician apply gentle Medicines that may gradually cure the mind, and ſo heal the Soul; The Judg ſhould be an Inſtructer.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:62369:27"/>
            <p n="2">2. If the Judg cannot by ſuch means re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the faulty, then ſhould he pray for him, beſeeching the Author of Life to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligehen the mind that the man fall not under the rigors of the Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such Officers ſhould ſee that Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be examined, and if any of them be found falſe Witneſs, the Officers ſhould pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They in duty ought to ſpeak kindly to the Priſoner, treat him, though an Offender, as a Son of the Church; offer him mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he asks for it, to let him know his fault, and his Accuſers what they are, that he may clear himſelf; by theſe gentle ways it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible he may be induced and perſwaded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent publickly if need be, and not ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his credit, which were it loſt by ſuch act, is abundantly recompenſed by the ſalvation of the Soul.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Such Office ought to leave the poſſeſſion of the temporal Goods entire to the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; for they are his right, and without injury to his ſpiritual Lord may be retained.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, ſuch office ſhould take the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent under its wing, cover the fault as much as diſcretion will allow, receive him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church again; forgive, love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62369:27"/>him as a Neighbour or Brother, and the rather, as one whom their care hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered from great ſin, and advanced to a new hope of glory.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee whether theſe things be found in this Office, the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and ſo,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Firſt, They are ſo ſo far from expreſſing love to their Priſoner, that they purſue him with extream hatred, keep him a Priſoner for ten or twelve years in ſome dark place, where he may neither ſee the Sun, nor ſpeak with any other than the Goaler.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) So far from praying for him, that they curſe him, and openly in the very Court uſe him like a Dog, deviſing new crimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him that they may deſtroy him; for 'tis the way of their dealing never to let go a Captive.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Inſtead of puniſhing, they reword, falſe witneſſes, and beſtow Salleries upon them.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) They never deal with a Priſoner with any reſpect to his temper and nature, or candidly offer him his pardon; nay, as if the Priſoner were a Beaſt to be ſtarved, they with-hold his food from him.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) They conceal the Names and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Accuſers; or deny them if they be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62369:28"/>gueſſed at by the Priſoner.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) They are ſo far from reſtoring goods, that they ſpoil Wife and Children of the Goods, which of right pertained unto them.</p>
            <p n="7">(7.) So far from preſerving your good name, that they divulge the faults in the Theatre, expoſe them to the diſgrace of a Sambenito, whip them openly, condemn them to the Gallies, until at laſt they have ſpoiled them of life, honour and Eſtates: on the whole matter we might enquire of theſe Judges, and appeal to all that live in the Learned World, whether the love, faith, prayers, chriſtianity, tenderneſs for their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the truth, juſtice, mercy of this Court may be found: whether ought of theſe are in this Office, where barbarous cruelty and Tyranny are the whole of its conſtitution, ſo apparently none can deny it?</p>
            <p>The third Title, is <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> that is, a ſcrutiny or ſearch into ſecrets, that they may be manifeſted for truths ſake; and this method as a part of the holy Government God did preſcribe, when by <hi>Moſes</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1. <hi>That the Prophet who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to draw away the people to ſtrange Gods, ſhould be puniſhed with death becauſe he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62369:28"/>had ſpoken to turn them from the Lord their God.</hi> Such a kind of Inquiſition Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to us in that Caution, <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and beware of thoſe that come to you in ſheeps cloathing, but inwardly they are ravening Wolves.</hi> Here the very Eſſence of the ſearch lieth in an impartial enquiry for the Truth in a matter that was hidden: Now let us enquire whether this Tribunal may in this ſenſe be ſaid to be an Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which in very deed wants both name and thing, according to this notion, of an Inquiſition: They enquire not diligently after Crimes to amend the Criminal, but earneſtly hunt after Temporal Eſtates, to ſeize them. Of Old the Eſtates of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized ones were not adjudged to the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> but to the Fires; now the Goods of ſuch are adjudged neither to the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> nor to the Fires, but to Robbing Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors. Inſtead of producing the truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, this Tribunal brings Lies openly to open view, and by falſe Witneſs and Cheats condemns Innocents; they tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiate falſhoods, and then proclaim them truths; they contrive greateſt injuſtices with greateſt ſecreſie; they condemn Innocents by wiles, and ſmother their righteous Cauſe,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62369:29"/>which they never ſuffer to be pleaded; this their Inquiſition it ſuppreſſeth truth, and murthers Innocents, and enquires what gain from the Execution, never what righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Judgment. By all this it appears the Tribunal is neither Holy, nor an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, nor an Inquiſition. Now let's enquire whether it proceed by any Moral Doctrines of Vertue; whether Juſtice, or Fortitude, or Temperance, or Prudence ſteer their proceedings; they are; by what is written already convicted to act no whit like Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; let us now ſee whether they act like Moral, Heathen Philoſophers.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall begin firſt with Juſtice, a Vertue which teacheth a man to lay his own and another mans Cauſe in an equal Balance, and makes the Judge to remember that he who now judgeth another mans Cauſe, muſt have his own judged e're long; that he muſt not wreſt judgment in favour of perſons, nor ſubvert judgment; that it concerns him moſt to exerciſe judgment perfectly, neither by too much lenity ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, nor with a cruel mind, and thirſty of revenge, torment the guilty: He muſt not look to any reward, nor do what may be condemn'd and puniſht by his Superiour
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62369:29"/>who made him Judge. Juſtice will make a Judge diligent in examining Cauſes, and weighing them again and again, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with wiſe and skilful men e're Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence be paſſed. When the juſtneſs of a Cauſe appears, a Judge ſhould have ſuch a brave reſolution and fortitude, that none ſhould be able to fright him into an unjuſt, or from a juſt Sentence; he ſhould without Cowardiſe protect and acquit the Innocent, and without Cowardiſe puniſh the guilty Offenders: He ſhould dare to paſs an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Sentence, upon a mature enquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cauſe of every one, that is brought before him into judgment. Farther, the Judge ſhould be of a very temperate and of a well-compoſed frame, able with patience to hear all Parties and Cauſes, and without prejudices toward the Cauſe, with paſſions ſubdued to Reaſon, Juſtice and Equity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the perſons, to diſtinguiſh and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the right from the wrong, the good from the bad, which no man in the uproar of paſſions can ever be able to do. Now on view it will appear, how naked and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of theſe Vertues this Court is, how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Inquiſition is rul'd by theſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. What Juſtice is there, where all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62369:30"/>concern'd are not openly produced, and where the Plea and Judgment is made ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, partially, and deſigning to take the Prey? What greater injuſtice, then firſt to deviſe Crimes, and charge them on Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, to the taking away their life, and next to ſeize their Eſtates, and rob the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor and his Heirs? If Murthers and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries may commend the Juſtice of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Court, here's Juſtice enough! their Prudence hath no more of that Vertue, than helliſh, perfidious, and perjurious contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances have of it; and very often their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence proclaims it ſelf, and their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues are brought to light, to the reproach and juſt condemnation of their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. In a word, they are not prudent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to act juſtly, nor prudent enough to conceal their injuſtice; their courage to own an Innocent, to ſave his life, reſtore him to liberty, and preſerve his Eſtate out of the hands of their bloody Crew, hath not one inſtance that I do know of; if one or two in an age could be found, that would willingly favour a righteous Cauſe, and right a rich wealthy perſon accus'd, ſuch dare not thwart the covetous, griping, and ſpoiling deſigns of their Partners; afraid
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62369:30"/>they are of one another, and of their cheating Inſtruments they uſe, every way they are inſlaved to a baſe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, that hath no more of Fortitude in it, than it hath of Mercy or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. Now ſuch can never be of a calm and even temper; they envy, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge, and hate, which are Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that ever hurry men, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate their proceedings: an immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate thirſt after the rich Eſtates of Condemned Perſons prevails with them to ſay they were guilty, nay to condemn them as guilty, who had no greater fault but they were too rich, and held their Eſtates gotten by the Right that Induſtry and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs do give, from the hands of that Inquiſition which is like it ſelf in covetouſneſs and injuſtice, two very unequal diſtributers of what they can lay hold of. But we'll diſmiſs them with their Theology and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, neither of which attends this
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62369:31"/>Tribunal, or the Judges thereof; and now let us conſider, whether the States-men and Polititians may allow this <hi>Tribunal</hi> any room in well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Governments, whether King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms or Commonwealths. And here, ſince Reaſon of State is the Helm by which they adminiſter the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is a certain myſterious Frame or Body that is ſubject to the changes that time does produce, which for the moſt part are changes for the worſe, like the changes of the Natural body by predominant humors needing a Phyſitian, who may by proper and gentle applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons purge out peccant humors, and preſerve the body: So the prudent Statiſt, the Soveraign Authority is concerned to uſe thoſe means which may carry off the redundant and threatning humors, from which ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth danger to the Publick; but it were a very pernicious courſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62369:31"/>ſuch means as would deſtroy the whole, or cut off an uſeful member of the Community. How greatly hath the Kingdom of <hi>Spain</hi> been endama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the over-violent Phyſick the Inquiſitors give to that Kingdom? This cut off the United <hi>Netherlands</hi> from the Kingdom of <hi>Spain,</hi> and in the cutting them off, <hi>Spain</hi> bled al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to death: ſhould a States-man have permitted this? and yet ſorer and more grievous calamities muſt be expected, unleſs this rigorous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition be removed. Would not reaſon of State perſwade to correct with tenderneſs, to the honour of the Families which are allied to the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals? but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere a <hi>Sambenito</hi> diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth whole Families, which are diſgracefully uſed, when once their name is publiſhed in the Writing which is ſixt on the <hi>Sambenito,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the names of the Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: It is of ill tendency, to caſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62369:32"/>on many for the offence of one; beſide, reaſon of State ſhould incouarge induſtry, and preſerve the goods and riches of the Subject: But behold the Inquiſition, a Court that does by all ill Arts contrive the confiſcating and ſeiſing of Eſtates, whereby whole Families, all at once utterly ruin'd, cry out againſt man's injuſtice, and appeal to the Juſtice of God! Would any well-governed State allow an abſolute and unaccountable Office to oppreſs and ruine the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject? Is he a wiſe States-man that advanceth Officers to a Power of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning, robnidg, and murthering their fellow-ſubjects, with an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance they ſhall never be called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for it? yet ſo is the Inquiſition impowred, if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be (as frequently it happens that he is) preſent in a ſolemn Act: The firſt thing theſe Inquiſitors do is this, they require him to ſwear he will not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62369:32"/>contravene their Sentence. Thus by Oath they ſecure their Proceſs, and advance their Clerical Cap above the Kings Crown in their Proceſſes; the pride of theſe Inquiſitors is like all the reſt of their exceſſes, 'tis grown to a Proverb in Spain,
<note place="margin">Con el Reg. eon Inquiſition chiton.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſilent before the King, and the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi> It is intollerable tyranny the Inquiſition uſeth, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning men to moſt ſevere uſages; that Friends may be forced to pay down Money for the mitigating the rigorous execution; in diſabling the Condemned for any Office or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that his Friends may be drawn to purchaſe the priviledge by great ſums of Money. Thus, like Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcencies, they ſtarve the body to feed themſelves.</p>
            <p>Three things they are notoriouſly buſie about.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62369:33"/>
            <p n="1">1. They murther fellow-ſubjects, and damn their Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They rob Families, and leave them to poverty and ſhame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſcatter the people, and drive them out of the Kingdom; whereas they ſeize one, many run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from their cruelty, and leave their own Country deſolate.</p>
            <p>In three things they are more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt than Heathens.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Concealing of Accuſers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Preſent ſpoiling of Goods.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Secret Priſons.</p>
            <p>In three things they act like. Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Expecting a Veneration becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saints, while they are Devils In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſecrating the ignominious <hi>Sambenito,</hi> and making it a ſacred Veſtment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Placing them with the Images of their Saints in their Churches.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:62369:33"/>
            <p>In three things they act like the Devil.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They have a Priſon like Hell it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Familiars like Fiends.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Torments that exceed the power of any to bear them, and live.</p>
            <p>They are worſt of Tyrants in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Forbidding all converſe with any, though their Wives deſire it; nay, ſtripping their Wives of their Bracelets and Ear-rings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are both Enemies to their Perſons, and Judges of the Cauſe, from whom no Appeal is permitted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All they do againſt Innocents is juſtified with this, <hi>The Inquiſition hath done it, and ſince it pleaſed them, it muſt not be complain'd of.</hi> They are ſalvage as the moſt Barbarous, without reſpect to their Sex; Women are badly treated by them, Virgins ſhamefully beaten, Priſoners ſtarved, and their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62369:34"/>Debts not paid out of their Eſtates confiſcated. This is the true temper of theſe Inquiſitors, they are made up of what is worſt in Barbarous, Tyrannical, Idolatrous, Heatheniſh and Diabolical tempers. The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular view of this Court of Blood caſts me into an amazement, that a King, with ſuch Councillors as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King, ſhould ſuffer ſo tyrannical and cruel a Power, which without much noiſe, and without any Juſtice, hath eaten out the Glory, Strength, and Unity of that Monarchy, and like a fretting Moth hath marred all that was the beauty of it.</p>
            <p>Awake ye Philoſophers, Lawyers, Divines, ye States-men of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhake off that Lethargick ſleepineſs which hath for two hundred and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, more or leſs, kept you deaf to the Cryes of Murther'd Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents! Awake and ſee how much
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62369:34"/>Glory you have loſt by this Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions unrighteouſneſs! Look into their ſtately Structures, there you'l find the ſpoils of your Families, and your Butcher'd Friends! Awake and hearken what your Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſay of this Tribunal, <hi>Engliſh, French, Dutch, German, Turks,</hi> and all with deteſtation abhorring that which is made up of Blood, Rapine, Cruelty, and Hypocriſie: Let it no longer alienate your Neighbours e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, ſuppreſs your own Honour, nor provoke the Wrath and Juſtice of Heaven againſt you; the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood, ſhed in great abundance by them, cryes to the Throne of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; the aſhes of burnt Bones, the depredations of rich Families, the undeſerved ignominy that hath been caſt on Noble Families: In a word, their Iniquity, well nigh grown to its fulneſs, cryes out for Vengeance on them who acted, and on you who
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62369:35"/>ſuffer'd ſuch Villanies. He that ſits at the right hand of the Father, will e're long deſtroy thoſe Murtherers: A Fire ſhall ariſe out of the <hi>North</hi> that ſhall burn you up, and judge you, as you have judged others; when there ſhall be Bleſſings from God on thoſe Monarchies, whoſe Kings and Councils have rul'd their Subjects by Juſtice, and abhorr'd ſuch cruel Tribunals, ſuch Wolves in Sheep skins; from whoſe rage and inſatiable blood-thirſtineſs, let the good Lord deliver thee, kind Reader, and all the Lovers of Truth and Peace. So prays <hi>James Salgado.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="translators_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:62369:35"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REader, the Author ſpeaks but what theſe Learn'd Authors added here have ſpoken, and thou mayſt believe, and make good uſe of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—Quae quoniam ſeveriſſime in capita &amp; fortunas hominum, prave de Religione ſentientium inquirit, Inquiſitionis nomen ſortita eſt. <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> ad. An. <hi>1547.</hi> Augebat horrorem perverſa &amp; praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stera Judiciorum forma, quae contra Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uralem Equitatem &amp; omnem legitimum rdinem in juriſdictione illa explicanda
<pb facs="tcp:62369:36"/>obſervatur; tum etiam Immanitas Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum quibus plerunque contra veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, quicquid delegatis Judicibus libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, à miſeris &amp; innocentibus reis ut ſe cruciatibus eximerent, per vim extorque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur. <hi>Thuan.</hi> Hiſt. ſui. Temp. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ad. an. <hi>1547.</hi> This Inquiſition — defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of no Vertue, but Justice and Mercy, Sir <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> Speculum Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropae, <hi>p. 112.</hi> — Preſſing mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, whom they charge under an high degree of Mortal Sin and Damnation—to approach their neareſt and deareſt Friends, if they know or but ſuſpest them to be culpable thereof, <hi>idem.</hi> Converted in ſome places to an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no leſs of Civil than Eccleſiaſtical Tyranny— And <hi>Spain</hi> would with the deareſt things it hath redeem it—<hi>idem. p. 113.</hi> The Rack of mens Souls— An invention fitter for the Religion of <hi>Antiochus, Domitian,</hi> or <hi>Mahomet, idem, p. 114. Ed.</hi> Quart. <hi>1629.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62369:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
